# MICHAEL DAVIS, I.O.M

Indianapolis, IN • 317.519.5392 • <u>Michael@GaugeResearch.com</u>
<u>LinkedIn | Website | Tableau</u>

## ENGAGEMENT MANAGER / ACTIVE TS/SCI CLEARANCE.

Senior business executive who leads government and business clients and connects the decision-making needs of leaders, executives, and stakeholders to better informed data analysis. Recognized for initiative and leadership in directing clients, customers, and businesses with a collaborative research-based, data-driven analytics approach. Over fifteen years of executive leadership in CEO, VP, and consulting roles demonstrating success in restructuring, creating, and growing productive organizations. Active TS/SCI Clearance.

## WORK EXPERIENCE AND RESPONSIBILITIES

Resultant | Indianapolis, IN

2021 - 2022

### **Engagement Manager**

- Responsible for all aspects of project management with multiple state agencies and teams.
- Served as the sole point of contact for clients and works with them to acquire a full understanding of their business, technologies, and key resources across all levels of the organization to solve complex technology projects.
- Led a 25-member cross-functional (engineering, data science, business intelligence, organizational
  management, UI/UX, data governance, project management) strategic government account with Indiana
  Department of Education to build a Graduates Prepared to Succeed dashboard using statewide longitudinal
  data covering seventeen key metrics used to evaluate the state, schools, and individual students.
- Led a strategic government account with the Indiana Management Performance Hub to analyze data and find solutions to the opioid crisis.
- Directed a team to create a "pilot hiring analysis tool" for an airline company to project future shortfalls in the number of pilots available to fly routes.
- Managed internal finances and business development activities for my clients (\$7.02M portfolio).
- Performed contract management for associated accounts, managed client capital and client need forecasting.
- Additional roles included: Program Manager, Technical Delivery Manager, Project Manager, Subject Matter Expert, and Onboarding Champion.

Gauge Research | Indianapolis, IN

2007 - present

### **Owner & President**

- Own and operate a consulting firm serving businesses in data/business analytics, public opinion research, demographic analysis, marketing, and organizational management.
- Led team in collecting precinct level election results from all 50 states for multiple races over several election cycles for a large statewide association. Standardized data and added U.S. Census demographic data through an API to conduct election analysis, identify trends, and create maps and Tableau visualizations.
- Extracted, cleaned, digested, standardized, and created data entry forms and Tableau visualizations from large amounts of gaming data for a multi-state news organization.

Enterprise Washington | Bellevue, WA

2013 - 2017

## **President & CEO**

- Led the state's preeminent business association for grassroots advocacy, political research, marketing analytics, and independent expenditure campaigns.
- Redesigned The Business Institute of Washington, Washington Voter Research, and multiple PACs. Responsible for the organization's operations, marketing, strategy, fundraising, social media, financials, and team. Worked closely with boards of directors, clients, members, vendors, and investors.
- Grew organizations to combined income of \$3.32M with seven full-time employees and 75 part-time employees.

# MICHAEL DAVIS, I.O.M

Indianapolis, IN • 317.519.5392 • Michael@GaugeResearch.com

## Enterprise Washington (continued)

- Increased fundraising by 218% (\$1.30M) and won 80% of campaigns.
- Successfully led the organizations through a complete reorganization of the mission, board of directors, staff, strategic plan, membership dues structure, employee health care insurance plan, organizational bylaws, membership programs, and an office relocation to a larger space.
- Created a statewide database of 7 million residents with 4,000 data points per person with extensive issue and audience modeling based on consumer data, demographics, and social media use.
- Created Washington Voter Research to conduct survey research and organize a field operations team consisting of up to 75 surveyors.

## BIPAC | Washington, D.C.

2010 - 2013

### **Senior Vice President**

- Served on senior management team of independent, bipartisan membership organization.
- Directed all activities related to the elections division and managing nine team members.
- Conducted first-ever nationwide ad buyout of YouTube by a political candidate or organization.
- Led the development of building a nationwide database of over 200 million individuals to utilize in digital marketing and advocacy campaigns.

Indiana Chamber of Commerce | Indianapolis, IN

2004 - 2010

#### Vice President of Political Affairs

- Served on senior management team with 50 staff for the state's leading pro-business advocacy organization with over 26,000 members and customers.
- Ran all activities related to one of the country's largest state or local chamber of commerce PACs, *Indiana Business for Responsive Government* (IBRG), and its five-person team.
- Prepared autonomous departmental budgets totaling \$2M.
- Launched the online Indiana Prosperity Project to educate citizens on elections and business issues.

## EDUCATION/CREDENTIALS

- Bachelor of Arts, Political Science; Minor: Economics Indiana University, Bloomington, IN
- TS/SCI clearance (Active)
- Data Analytics and Visualization Executive Education Certificate Butler University, Indianapolis, IN
- Visual Analytics with Tableau Certificate, Essential Design Principles for Tableau Certificate, and Fundamentals of Visualization with Tableau Certificate – University of California, Davis, CA
- Customer Analytics Certificate The University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA
- Professional certificate in Nonprofit Organizational Management
- U.S. Chamber of Commerce Institute for Organization Management (I.O.M.)

## SKILLS

Consulting: Leadership, management, public speaking, presentations, teamwork, problem-solving

Project Management: Agile Project Management, Jira, Azure DevOps, SharePoint

Programs / Languages: Tableau, Python, SQL, HTML, CSS, JSON, JavaScript

Other: Jupyter, VS Code, GitHub, Git Bash, Access, Advanced Excel, PowerPoint